Your Highness, please take a rest.
殿下 お休みください
You've been writing all day.
一日中お書きです
Hasn't Xiao Wuyi confessed yet?
蕭無衣はまだ罪を認めぬか
Forgive me, Your Highness.
殿下 お許しを
No matter how he's tortured,
いかなる拷問にも
Xiao Wuyi remains silent.
蕭無衣は一言も発しませぬ
He only asked the jailers for a brush and ink
獄卒に筆と墨を求め
to finish his military book.
兵法書を完成させたいと
Without Your Highness's permission,
殿下の勅旨がなければ
the jailers didn't dare to give him those.
獄卒は渡しかねております
So Xiao Wuyi dips his finger in blood and continues to write.
蕭無衣は指に血をつけ書き続けていると
What about the divorce paper?
では離縁状は
He didn't write it.
書いておりませぬ
Then force him to write!
ならば無理にでも書かせろ
Once it's written, send it to Prince Jing'an's Mansion!
書かせたら靖安王府へ送れ
Tell the Commandant of Justice that
廷尉に伝えよ
the evidence of Prince Jing'an's Household's treason and corruption is conclusive.
靖安王府の密通と汚職の証拠は固いと
If he can't get Xiao Wuyi's confession,
蕭無衣から供述書が取れねば
Xiao Ju's will do,
蕭駒のでもよい
or Xiao Yao's!
蕭堯のでも構わぬ
Grand Tutor was right.
太傅の言うとおりだ
Prince Jing'an's Household is too stubborn.
靖安王府の一家は実に強情だ
We might as well take this opportunity and completely bring them down.
いっそこの機に叩き折ってくれる
Yes.
はっ
Xiao and his 2 sons embezzled canal funds,
蕭氏親子三名は水路補修費を横領
illegally sold military supplies,
軍需品を横流し
and committed treason.
敵国に通じ国を売った
Their mansion is now sealed off.
これより王府を差し押さえる
By the Regent's grace,
監国の恩情により
those who are not members of the Xiao family may leave.
蕭氏の一族にあらざる者は立ち去るがよい
Anyone who refuses will be sealed inside the mansion immediately.
立ち去らぬ者は屋敷ごと封鎖する
Except for the Dowager Princess,
王大妃様を除き
everyone else has left.
他の者たちは皆 去りました
Master He is just a teacher hired by our family.
何先生は我が家が招いた師です
And Ruisheng is our physician.
蕊生は我が家が招いた医師です
Aren't they a goddaughter and a concubine?
養女と側室ではなかったのか
And what about the child?
それに あの子は
Master He belongs to the He family
何先生は 何氏の娘で
and has nothing to do with the Xiaos.
蕭氏とは無関係です
As for Yu Ruisheng,
そして虞蕊生は
she has never been part of Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
もとより靖安王府の者ではございません
She is an official of the Beifu Army Medical Office
彼女は北府軍医署の官吏で
and receives her salary from Beifu.
北府から俸禄を得ています
As for Duan Ziqi,
段子期に至っては
he is certainly not Xiao Wuyi's son.
なおのこと蕭無衣の息子ではありません
And the Dowager Princess—
そして王大妃様ですが
if I remember correctly,
私の記憶が正しければ
according to the laws of Ye, women over fifty awaiting trial
大鄴の法では 五十路を過ぎた婦人の罪は
can be confined at home.
自宅での禁錮が許されます
Is that right?
いかがです
As for me...
そして私は
What is that in your hand?
そなたが持つのは何だ
This is Young Lord Xiao's divorce paper.
これは蕭世子の離縁状です
Your Highness, the Regent wants you
監国殿下が世子妃様に
to think carefully for yourself.
ご自身の身の上をよくお考えになるよう申されました
Please convey my word
皆様 私の意向を
to Prince Qi.
岐王殿下にお伝えください
Tomorrow is the deadline.
明日が最終期限です
Report!
申し上げます
Your Highness,
殿下に申し上げます
Liu Zhaolin, an editor from Zhengtong Bookstore,
正通書局の撰修
has come to turn himself in.
柳昭林が自首いたしました
Wasn't Liu Zhaolin already...
柳昭林はすでに
Report!
申し上げます
Congratulations, Your Highness.
殿下 お祝い申し上げます
For what?
余に何の喜びがあるというのだ
Your Highness,
殿下に申し上げます
the blood stasis in Xiao Wuyi's brain has been there for nearly 3 years
蕭無衣の脳内の血瘀は３年近くになり
and has become a chronic illness.
持病と化しております
Rest assured, Your Highness.
殿下 ご安心を
Once his meridians are completely blocked,
経脈が完全に詰まれば
he won't survive.
もはや助かる道はございません
In my humble opinion,
私の愚見では
Xiao Wuyi will not live past this year.
蕭無衣は年内もたないかと存じます
How dare you!
無礼者
When did I ever say I wanted Xiao Wuyi dead?
余がいつ蕭無衣の命を求めると言った
I'm telling you.
よく聞け
If Xiao Wuyi doesn't recover,
もし蕭無衣が完治せねば
I will bury the entire Imperial Medical Bureau with him!
太医署ごと道連れにしてくれる
Get out!
下がれ
Yes.
はっ
If we don't eliminate Northern Qin
北秦を滅ぼさず
and reclaim our land,
故郷を取り戻さねば
there won't be true peace!
真の平和は訪れない
Yizhi.
易之さん
This is what you told me yourself
それは剣慷へ逃げる途中
while fleeing to Jiankang.
ご自身で言ったことですよ
Have you forgotten?
お忘れになったのです
Don't be trapped in the past
過去に囚われるな
and let it become your inner demon.
過去を心魔にするな
You are not this kind of person.
元はそんな方ではなかったでしょう
Report!
申し上げます
Your Highness,
殿下
the jailers said that
獄卒によれば
before Young Lord Xiao fainted, he said
蕭世子は気を失う前に
he had no crimes to confess,
認める罪はない とのことです
and that if he must confess,
どうしても罪を認めねばならぬのなら
this military book written in blood is his confession.
この血で書かれた兵法書が罪状だと
Summon Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚を参らせよ
Yes.
はっ
No.
いや
Forget it.
呼ぶな
Have Xie Jiayu go directly to the prison
謝嘉魚に直接 牢へ向かわせ
and take Xiao Wuyi out.
蕭無衣を連れ出させよ
Yes.
はっ
You dictate,
言え
and I'll write it down.
私が書こう
Anyone who uses formations...
およそ陣を用いる者は
Done.
よし
Can you go home with me now?
これで私と家に帰ってくれるの
Pack these manuscripts up
この書稿をまとめ
and give them to Prince Qi and the Department of State Affairs.
岐王と尚書台に渡せ
This is your life's work.
それはあなたの畢生の学びよ
If you teach them,
それを彼らに教えて
aren't you afraid of being replaced?
弟子に奥義を授け 師匠が食いっぱぐれる心配はないの
Isn't that exactly what I want?
それこそ我が望むところだ
Don't you want
望まないのか
there to be more Xiao Wuyis in Ye?
この大鄴に 蕭無衣が何人も現れることを
Are you really making your final arrange—
本当に身辺整理をする気
Even if you want to die,
死に急ぐつもりでも
you have to hold on for a few more years.
あと数年は持ちこたえろ
Right now,
今は
the world needs an invincible Xiao Wuyi.
天下には無敵の蕭無衣が必要だ
Let's go. Let's go home.
さあ 帰ろう
Let's go home.
帰るぞ
Let's go.
行くぞ
Wuyi!
無衣
Mother?
母上
Father?
父上
Brother?
兄上
You...
皆…
Let's go home.
家に帰るぞ
That's my son!
さすがは我が息子だ
Be gentle!
もっと優しく
How can he stand you patting him like that now?
今のあの子にそんな叩き方は堪えるわ
Let's go.
行こう
Okay.
ああ
Let's go home.
家に帰ろう
Why did you let Xiao Wuyi go?
なぜ蕭無衣を釈放した
You...
お前は
This was...
これは
This was the only chance to bring Prince Jing'an's Household down
靖安王府を倒し
and take back the command of Beifu Army!
北府兵の兵権を取り戻す唯一の好機だったのだぞ
Don't you want to avenge
実の母親の
your mother?
仇を討ちたくないのか
If Xiao Ju hadn't concealed the truth,
蕭駒が報告を隠さなければ
how could the An and Lu families have been wrongfully destroyed?
安陸の二氏が無実の罪で滅ぼされることもなかった
Xie Jiayu brought
謝嘉魚が持ってきました
the letters between you and the wet nurse of Prince Qi's Mansion,
あなた様と岐王府の乳母との書簡を
threatening to reveal my identity
私の素性を公にすると脅し
to make me let Xiao Wuyi go.
蕭無衣を釈放しろと
Should I have let him go or not?
釈放すべきでしたか それともせぬべきでしたか
So she came to me specifically that day
あの日 わざわざ私を訪ねてきたのは
for this?
このためだったとは
Oh, right, Liu Zhaolin turned himself in.
ええ 柳昭林が自首しました
Him?
彼は
He wouldn't dare say much.
何も言おうとはしません
Yes, he has committed suicide out of fear of punishment.
はい 罪を恐れて自害しました
The Commandant of Justice also went to Lane 3
廷尉は上河坊三巷を差し押さえに向かいました
trying to catch those scholars who had helped Liu Zhaolin
柳昭林に加担し
forge the embezzlement ledgers.
横領の帳簿を偽造した学徒らを捕らえようとしたが
Unfortunately, he was a step too late.
一歩遅かった
Also...
それから
Father,
父上
I only have one mother,
私の母はただ一人
and that is Prince Qi's Consort.
岐王妃様だけです
Back then, Prince Qi's Consort gave her life
かつて岐王妃様が その命と引き換えに
in exchange for my sister's life and mine.
私と妹を救ってくださいました
I have never had a 2nd mother.
私に二人目の母などおりません
Avenging her
母上の恨みは
is your obsession,
あなた様の心残りであって
not mine.
私のではありません
Hurry!
急げ
Did Liu Zhaolin mention
柳昭林は死ぬ前に
who gave him the orders before he died?
誰かの指示を受けたと供述は
No.
誰からも
He didn't?
指示は受けていないと
Liu Zhaolin's original surname was Pei.
この柳昭林は 本姓を裴と言い
He and He Yuanji, the former Heir's Consort of Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
靖安王府の前の世子妃 何元姫とは
were childhood sweethearts.
幼なじみでした
After He married into Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
何氏が靖安王府に嫁いだ後
he couldn't accept losing her,
彼は愛が実らなかったことで
so out of resentment,
恨みを抱き
he deliberately framed them.
陥れようと画策したのです
He even bribed the scholars in Lane 3 of Shanghe Ward
さらに上河坊三巷の学徒を買収し
to forge the evidence of corruption with him.
共に横領の証拠を偽造したと
When the matter was exposed,
事件が発覚すると
he committed suicide to atone for his crimes
自害して罪を償い
and clear the Xiao family's name.
蕭家の潔白を証明したとか
He was quite noble.
なかなか見事な男だな
It's you?
やはりお前か
The moment I was imprisoned,
私が投獄された時から
I was reminded of
あることを思い出していました
an old story that circulated
かつて上京の後宮で
in the inner palace of the Capital.
ささやかれていた古い話を
When you used the collapse of the grain canal
そして太傅が食糧輸送路の崩壊を罪とし
to try to wipe out the entire Prince Jing'an's Household,
我ら靖安王府の一族を皆殺しにしようとした
it further confirmed my guess.
これで私の推測が確信に変わりました
The rumors about you and Noble Concubine An back then
かつての太傅と安貴嬪のうわさは
were true.
まことだったのですね
Back then, you knew it was an unjust case,
あれが冤罪だと知りながら
yet you still sent the two noble families—
あなたは二大名家と
hundreds of lives—to the execution ground.
数百人の命を刑場に送った
What I am doing now
私の今の行いは
is merely returning an eye for an eye.
やられたらやり返しただけのこと
Back then, the noble families held absolute power.
当時 名家は権力を独占し
They defied the imperial authority
上は皇室を欺き
and oppressed the people,
下は民を虐げた
making life impossible for them
民は塗炭の苦しみを味わい
and leading rebel armies to rise up everywhere.
各地で義勇軍が蜂起した
So you could disregard right and wrong
だからといって 是非も問わず
and kill innocent people?
命を奪っていいと
The An and Lu families never committed treason!
安陸は国に背いてなどいない
Princess Pingning has been
平寧県主
secretly operating in the Capital and has obtained solid evidence.
上京に潜伏していた証拠はつかんでいる
In the An-Lu case back then,
当時の安陸の事件
you knew the truth
あなたは真相を知りながら
but did not report it.
報告しなかった
Oh, you, Xiao Ju.
蕭駒… お前というやつは
You earned your title as Prince Jing'an
お前の靖安王府の爵位は
on the blood of our noble families.
我ら名家の血の上に築かれたものだ
I admit
認めよう
I am not innocent.
私も潔白ではない
But for the poor scholars,
だが寒門のため
for Emperor and Empress Wenxi,
文熹帝と皇后
and even more, for Ye,
そして大鄴のために
I had to burn my boats.
背水の陣で臨むしかなかった
As for you, Grand Tutor,
だが太傅 あなたは
as the head of the noble families,
名家清流派の長だ
our stances are different.
私とあなたの立場は違う
But speaking of wrongful deaths,
だが理不尽な死と言えば
to whom should those poor scholars
安陸の二大名家の
wrongfully killed by the An and Lu families
刃に倒れた寒門の者たちは
cry out for justice?
誰に無念を訴えればいい
If the An and Lu families deserved to be punished
かつて安陸の二大名家が川筋を監修した件が
for overseeing the waterway construction back then,
罪に値するというなら
then dare you say Xiao Yao was entirely blameless
では今回の食糧輸送路の崩壊で
for the collapse of the grain canal?
蕭堯には 過失がなかったと断言できるか
Is he really innocent?
あの人は本当に無実なのかしら
Corruption and smuggling may have been false accusations,
横領と密輸は冤罪かもしれない
but the grain canal collapse—
でも兵糧路の崩落は
I don't think so.
そうとは限らない
Xiao Wuyi, you lied to me.
蕭無衣さん 嘘つき
You can see.
見えてるんでしょう
This is called locating things by sound.
音で位置を把握してるんだ
I have been practicing it for the past 2 years.
この２年 ずっと練習してきた
Sooner or later, I will lose my sight.
いずれは見えなくなる
I can't be completely unprepared.
何の備えもなしじゃいられないだろ
Let go of me. Let me get up.
放して 起こして
Let go!
放しなさい
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣さん
Why didn't you tell me 2 years ago
血瘀がひどくなるって
that the blood stasis would keep getting worse?
なぜ２年前に教えてくれなかったの
You are cruel, planning to leave me behind.
ひどいわ 私を途中で見捨てるつもりだったのね
Aren't you afraid I'll back out?
私が心変わりするかもって思わなかったの
What can you do? Divorce me?
今さら婚約破棄でもする気か
After all, you've already burned the divorce paper.
離縁状なら お前が燃やしただろ
You...
もう
Why are you crying?
なぜ泣いてる
This blood stasis cannot be cured.
この血瘀は治せない
Even if I had told you,
お前に言っても
it would have only added to your worries.
悩みを増やすだけだ
But if you had told me earlier,
でも もっと早く教えてくれてたら
I wouldn't have left you in the past 2 years.
この２年 あなたのそばを離れなかったのに
And I wouldn't have been so oblivious,
のんきに構えて
thinking we still had plenty of time.
まだ時間があるなんて思わなかった
Alright.
よしよし
These past 2 years you've been following the map to find mines,
この２年 お前は鉱脈図を手に鉱床を探し
traveling thousands of miles
万里の道を行き
and seeing the world and all living beings.
天地を見て 人々と出会い
You opened branches of Miraculous Craft across Ye
その妙手を大鄴中に広め
to help the people.
民の暮らしを支えてきた
Are you happy?
楽しかっただろ
Your happiness is the most important thing.
お前が楽しく幸せでいることが何より大事だ
Xiao Wuyi, I'm telling you.
蕭無衣さん 言っておくけど
I haven't finished burning
この離縁状
the divorce paper.
まだ全部は燃えてないの
There's still half left.
半分残ってるわ
If you ever
もし今度
hide anything
また何か隠したり
from me again,
教えてくれなかったら
anyone who wants to be the Heir's Consort can have the title.
世子妃なんて誰がなってもいいわ
I'm not doing it anymore.
私はやめるから
Trying to trick me? You want to back out?
まだ騙す気なの 気が変わったの
My blueprints!
私の図面
Xiao Wuyi, you can see.
蕭無衣さん やっぱり見えてるじゃない
I can't see.
見えない
Ziqi, listen to me.
子期 母上の言うことを聞くのよ
If you ever meet
もし将来
someone like your father,
世子の父上のような人に出会ったら
stay away from him,
近づいちゃだめ
or he'll ruin your good name.
自分の看板に傷がつくわ
What kind of person is he?
世子の父上ってどんな人
To coax a lady,
女の人を喜ばせるために
he calls a terminal illness a cold.
不治の病を風邪だと言い
He doesn't take care of himself
体を大事にしない
and refuses to take his condition seriously.
分別のない人のことよ
But Mother,
でも母上
I don't want to study medicine in the future.
僕は医術を学びたくない
Then what do you want to study?
じゃあ何を学びたいの
I want to study poison.
毒の術を学びたい
Say that again.
もう一度言いなさい
I also want to learn Auntie Jiayu's mechanical skills.
嘉魚おば上のからくり術も学びたい
If I can combine the two of them,
２つを合わせれば
it will be very powerful.
きっとすごい威力になる
That day, I even saw...
この間 見たんだ
Mother, have mercy!
母上 ご勘弁を
Duan Ziqi, come back here!
段子期 戻ってきなさい
Hang out less with your Auntie Jiayu!
嘉魚おば上とあまりつるまないで
If you dare to touch her alchemy furnace,
あの人の練丹炉に一度でも触れたら
I'll chop off your hands!
この母が腕を切り落とすから
See?
あなた
What have you taught Ziqi?
子期に何を教えたの
It's clearly you who refuses to let go.
そっちが手を放さなかったくせに
What is this?
これは何
This is a cane I made for you.
お前のために作った杖だ
It has a mechanism inside.
中に仕掛けがある
It can be retracted into your sleeve when not in use.
使わぬ時は袖にしまえる
But you've learned to locate things by sound.
だが そなたは音で場所が分かるようになった
I don't think you need it.
もう要るまい
Who says I don't?
誰が要らぬと
Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚
Actually, the divorce paper I wrote in prison was fake.
実は 獄中で書いた離縁状は偽物だ
I never wanted to divorce you.
そなたと離縁する気など毛頭なかった
I know.
分かってる
Two years ago,
二年前
Ruisheng told me
蕊生から聞いた
there was a way to clear my blood stasis,
私の血瘀を消す方法があるが
but it was very risky.
危険が大きいと
If it failed,
もし失敗すれば
I could lose my life at any time.
いつ命を落としてもおかしくなかった
But for the sake of reform,
だが改制のため
I chose not to take that chance.
危険は冒せなかった
I'm sorry.
すまない
Call me selfish
身勝手だと言われようと
or shameless.
恥知らずと思われようと
Even knowing that I am destined to fail you,
そなたを裏切る運命だと分かっていても
I will never let you go.
決して手放しはしない
If Ruisheng knows you're not resting properly
蕊生姉様が あなたがちゃんと休まず
and that you're shedding tears,
涙を流していると知れば
she'll scold me again.
また私が叱られてしまうわ
She wouldn't dare.
まさか
You are my Heir's Consort.
そなたは私の世子妃だぞ
I lost my parents when I was young.
私は幼い頃に実の父母を亡くした
Mother,
母上も
Grand Tutor,
太傅も
Lejun, and Mao
楽君と阿茂も
have also left me one by one.
皆 私のもとを去っていった
My whole life,
私の人生は
it seems I've been learning how to say goodbye.
まるで別れの術を学び続けているかのよう
So don't worry.
だから心配しないで
I am very good at saying goodbye.
別れには慣れているから
Even if that day really comes
もし本当にその日が来て
and you leave me,
あなたが逝ってしまっても
I will cry for you for a month at most.
私が泣くのは せいぜい一月かしら
No, 3 months.
いや 三月だ
As long as you promise me one thing,
一つだけ約束してくれたら
you won't be breaking your promise.
あなたが約束を破ったことにはしないわ
Alright?
いい？
Tell me.
聞こう
Whether it is 3 years
三年でも
or 5 years,
五年でもいい
from today on,
今日から
forget the deadline Ruisheng gave you.
蕊生姉様に言われた期限は忘れて
No matter when,
どんな時も
as long as you remember that I am waiting for you,
私が待っていると思い出して
can you hold on for me
私のために
for as long as you can?
一刻でも長く生きて
Let's go as far
行けるところまで
as we can together.
一緒に行きましょう
I only need you to do your best,
あなたが全力を尽くしてくれればいい
and I will do my best too.
私も全力を尽くすわ
Then I won't see it as you letting me down.
そうすれば裏切られたとは思わない
But 3 months is just too short.
だが三月は短すぎる
It really is too short.
本当に短すぎる
How about 3 years?
三年はどうだ
Forget me
私が死んでから三年
3 years after I die, okay?
そのあとで私を忘れてくれ
Can't you just say you will try harder
「もう少し頑張って
to stay alive?
死なないようにする」って言えないの？
Okay.
分かった
Rest assured. Although His Highness doesn't care about his life,
安心して 世子様は命を惜しまないけど
as a physician,
医者の私としては
I still care about my reputation.
看板が大事なの
I will do everything I can to keep him alive.
全力を尽くして 彼を生かしてみせる
Thank you, Ruisheng.
姉様 ありがとうございます
Fortunately, with you here now,
幸い今はあなたがいるから
my chances of success are actually higher.
むしろ勝算は上がったわ
But he has put off treatment for so long.
でも もうずいぶん長く患っています
Life is truly magical.
命とは不思議なもので
Sometimes, the will to live matters more than anything else.
時に 生きたいという意志が何より大切になるの
In my eyes, Xiao Wuyi, the commander of Beifu,
かつて私の目に映る北府の統帥 蕭無衣は
was once more like
まるで冷たい兵器のよう
a cold lifeless weapon.
命が宿っていなかった
He gave almost everything for this world.
彼は天下のため ほとんど全てを捧げてきた
He clearly took the world as his responsibility,
天下を己が任と心得ているのに
but it seemed
だが
he had never been attached to anything in this world.
この世の草木一本にすら 未練がないかのようだった
Until he met you.
そなたに出会うまでは
People with aspirations cling to life,
志ある者は生に執着し
and martyrs seek death.
道に殉ずる者は死を求める
Jiayu.
嘉魚さん
You must hold onto him.
必ず彼を引き止めて
You know your days are numbered.
己の余命が短いと悟り
Five or ten years
5年や10年では
won't be enough to complete your grand plan.
心に抱く大業を成し遂げるには足りぬ
That's why you're in such a rush to complete the Beifu Reform.
だから北府の改制を急いでいるのだ
These past few days,
この数日
I've been reading the military strategies and essays
獄中でそなたが残した
you wrote in prison.
兵法の策論を読んでいた
You knew my background
私の素性を知りながら
but said nothing,
何も言わなかったのは
because you were certain
いずれ私がそなたの考えを認め
that I would eventually agree with you.
必ず北伐を行うと
You were also certain I would march north,
踏んでいたからか
weren't you?
そうであろう
Over 20 years have passed.
20年以上が過ぎ
How many survivors of Ye
多くの大鄴の民が
are being treated like cattle and slaves by Northern Qin
故郷の地で
on the lands that once belonged to Ye?
北秦に牛馬のごとく虐げられている
To this day,
今日に至るまで
they are still waiting for Crown Prince Wenxi.
彼らは文熹太子を待ち続けている
But what about 30 or 40 years from now?
だが30年後 40年後はどうだ
Yizhi, you are different from the Grand Tutor.
易之 そなたは太傅とは違う
The noble families don't care about reclaiming our land
名家は故郷を思わず
and are content to indulge in pleasure.
享楽にふける
But Prince Qi
だが岐王は
will never forget the fall of Qizhou.
岐州の陥落を永遠に忘れぬ
But I am not a pawn!
だが私は駒ではない
My life and honor
この李易之の生死栄辱
must never depend on
蕭無衣 そなた一人の
your passing whims!
善悪に委ねることはできぬ
Prince Jing'an's Household
靖安王府と
and the Beifu Army
北府軍は
must both be contained!
どちらも抑え込まねばならぬ
Are you counting on the noble families?
名家に頼るとでも
You know better than I do
私以上に分かっているはずだ
that they are the true blight of Ye.
名家こそが大鄴の膿だと
Yizhi,
易之
if you rule your people through manipulation,
術で人を御せば
they will manipulate you in return.
人もまた術で応じる
Why not
いっそ
try another way?
やり方を変えてはどうか
Bravo! Bravo!
よし よし
Bravo!
よし
Where is the money?
金は
Where is my money?
俺の金はどうした
Listen, brat.
おい ガキ
You are not leaving today without paying.
金を出さねえと 帰れると思うな
Give us the money!
金を出せ
-Give us the money! -Behave yourself!
出せ おとなしくしろ
You should've done that earlier. Let's go.
さっさと出せばよかったんだ 行くぞ
Mao, I am hungry.
兄上 腹が減りました
Thank you.
感謝する
Move!
どけ
Out of the way!
どけ どけ
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
so many refugees are begging outside Jiankang.
剣慷城の外で これほど多くの流民が物乞いをしているのに
Why is the Beifu Army doing nothing?
なぜ北府兵は動かぬのだ
Have you ever thought about
考えたことはあるか
what Ye will be like in the future?
未来の大鄴がどうあるべきか
I hope for a Ye of peace and prosperity,
私が望むのは 国が泰平で民が安らかな大鄴だ
with capable generals defending the borders,
国境には戦に長けた武将がおり
a righteous and well-governed court,
朝廷は清廉で
and scholars of both noble and humble origins making full use of their talents.
名家と寒門が共に才を発揮する世だ
They are the scholars of humble origins hiding in Xiyuan.
彼らこそ 西苑に身を潜める寒門の学徒だ
Why were Liu Zhaolin and those
柳昭林と
poor scholars hiding in Xiyuan
西苑に身を潜める貧しい学徒らは
willing to help Xie Huaigui?
なぜ謝懐帰を助けたかと言えば
It's simply because
権力者にすがらねば
relying on the powerful is their only path to an official career.
出世の道が開かれぬからにすぎぬ
If not forced by circumstances,
学問を志す者も やむにやまれねば
what scholar would willingly soil their brush and clothes?
誰が筆や衣を汚そうか
Tell me.
言ってみろ
Should I give them another chance?
彼らにもう一度 機会を与えるべきだろうか
Your Highness saved my life.
殿下はかつて この命をお救いくださいました
To me,
私にとって
Your Highness
殿下は
is a god who guided my soul through the darkness.
闇に魂を照らす神のようなお方です
If today,
もし今日
Your Highness is willing to give them another chance,
殿下がもう一度機会をお与えくだされば
they will surely dedicate their entire lives
彼らもきっと 一生を
to you.
殿下に捧げることでしょう
Forgive me, Your Highness. I misspoke.
殿下 お許しください 失言でした
Get them some new clothes.
彼らに新しい服を着替えさせよ
Yes.
はっ
We can establish the Nine-Rank System,
中正を設け
with family background, literary talent, and moral conduct
家柄 文才 徳行を基準に
as the criteria for ranking.
品階を分け
Only nobles can attain the upper ranks.
上品は名家のみが得られる
You still see the Lantai gathering as a private tool for the nobles.
先生はまだ蘭台会を名家の私物だとお考えか
I have been Regent for 3 years.
私が監国して三年
I established provincial schools
州学を広め
and expanded libraries.
書庫を拡充した
Talents from humble origins are no longer what they once were.
寒門の俊才も もはや昔の彼らではない
Therefore,
ゆえに
I will change the Lantai gathering into spring examinations,
私は蘭台会を春考に改め
letting the commoners and nobles compete on equal footing.
燕雀と鴻鵠が 天を目指し競い合うようにする
Your Highness, the hierarchy of rites is like a guiding star.
殿下 礼法は天の北斗です
If old systems are recklessly changed,
みだりに旧制を改めれば
I fear the order of the realm will fall into chaos.
天地の綱紀を乱しかねません
Master, you have helped me reach this position.
先生が私をこの立場に追いやっておいて
What's the point of talking about the order of the realm now?
今更 宗法や綱紀とはな
Your Highness, holding a spring exam requires massive effort.
殿下 春考の実施は 大変な骨折りです
Moreover, the children of noble families
しかも名家の子弟は
have studied the classics since childhood.
幼き頃より経籍を学び
The great scholars are all at our schools.
天下の碩学は皆 学府に集い
And the academies
その書院もまた
are all operated by the major noble families.
各名家が運営するものです
They spend fortunes to gather the wise
財を投じ 賢良を集め
and have already recruited all the elite of the realm.
すでに九州の精鋭を独占しております
Could it be
まさか
that you are afraid the nobles can't beat the humble scholars?
先生は名家が寒門に負けるのを恐れているのですか
If Your Highness insists on doing this,
殿下がどうしてもと仰せなら
I have one condition.
臣より一つ条件がございます
Pose a challenging question for all students and have them discuss
天下の学徒らに難題を出させていただきます
the difficulties and solutions in waterway construction.
川筋の監修の難しさと その解決法を論じさせます
This is a universal challenge.
これは天下の難題です
Let's see which of the two groups, the nobles and the humble scholars,
名家の子弟と寒門の者 どちらが
truly understands Ye's state affairs.
真に大鄴の国事を理解しているか 見極めましょう
If, as Your Highness claims,
もし殿下の仰せの通り
the nobles can't beat the humble scholars,
名家の子弟が寒門に及ばぬなら
I am willing to retire,
この老臣は官を辞して故郷へ戻り
reopen my academy,
学舎を再び開いて
devote myself to scholarship,
学問に専念し
and no longer get involved in political affairs.
二度と政には関わりませぬ
You must be joking.
先生 ご冗談を
I approve of this.
よかろう この件 許可する
The time for this year's Lantai gathering has been set.
今年の蘭台会の日程が決まったぞ
What? When?
何だと いつだ
When? Let me see.
いつなんだ 見せろ
Wait.
待たれよ
By order of the Eastern Palace,
東宮令だ
this year's Lantai gathering is canceled
今年の蘭台会は中止
and replaced by a spring examination.
春考に改める
Talents will be selected
家柄を問わず
regardless of family background.
人材を抜擢する
Regardless of family background?
家柄を問わずだと
-Canceled? A spring examination? -Regardless of family background?
中止して 春考を 家柄を問わず
It's an order from the Eastern Palace?
東宮令
Xie Huaigui!
謝懐帰
Xie Huaigui, come out!
謝懐帰 出てこい
Why is the Lantai gathering canceled?
なぜ蘭台会を中止するんだ
Why is it canceled? Why set a spring examination?
なぜ中止する なぜ春考を設けるのだ
-Xie Huaigui!
謝懐帰 謝懐帰
Come out!
出てこい
Return to the mansion.
屋敷へ戻る
Why is it canceled?
なぜ中止なんだ
Xie Huaigui!
謝懐帰
The spring exam will start in 3 days.
三日後には春考だというのに
Your brother spends all day reading storybooks.
兄さんは一日中 話本に夢中で
His heart lies not here,
あの方は全く関心なく
but among the mountains and rivers.
山水に心を寄せ
He frequents music houses all day.
一日中 楽坊に入り浸っています
The gazette says
邸報によると
this examination
今回の選抜は
only has 2 subjects: Confucian classics and policy essays.
儒経と策論の二科目のみだとか
Students take the exam anonymously,
学徒は皆 匿名で受験し
and papers are graded anonymously.
採点も匿名で行われると
Five matches are ranked as superior,
五つ合えば「上」
three or four as middle,
三つか四つで「中」
and two as inferior.
二つで「下」だそうです
I don't know if it's true or not.
真偽は不明ですが
Yuanji.
元姫
You are now
今やあなたは
the head of our He family.
何家の采配を振るう立場なのですよ
If your father and brother
もしお父上や兄上たちが
fail to secure a good future,
出世できなければ
who in the entire He family
この何家一同 年寄りも若者も
will truly submit to you?
誰があなたを認めましょう
Yuanji! Did you hear me?
元姫 聞いていますか
You need to talk to your father and brother.
お父上たちを説得しに行かねば
Throughout history, talent selection
古来より賢才の登用は
has always been based on family background.
すべて家柄や身分で決まります
As the saying goes, those of humble origins cannot reach high ranks,
いわゆる「上品に寒門なく
and those from noble families do not fall to low ranks.
下品に世族なし」です
Prince Qi has now set a spring examination.
岐王が設けた春考は
Regardless of noble or humble status,
貴賤を問わず
or connections,
家柄も問わず
as long as one has real talent,
真の才覚さえあれば
they can take the exam.
誰でも受験できるのです
If they truly appoint officials based on ability,
本当に才に応じて官吏を登用するなら
it would be a great achievement.
それは大きな功徳です
But they are unwilling to take the exam.
でも 彼らが受けなければ
What's the point?
何の意味もありませぬ
Auntie He.
何おば上
Don't worry.
ご心配なさらないで
I have come up with a good idea.
よい考えが浮かびました
Isn't the path forward for the He family
何氏の活路は遠くではなく
right in front of you?
目の前にありますわ
Your Highness,
世子妃様
are you making fun of us?
私たち母娘をからかっておいでですか
Yuanji,
元姫姉様
think about it.
よく考えてみて
I'm serious about this.
私のこの策は本気よ
Yuanji, don't listen to her nonsense.
元姫 あの者の戯言を聞いてはなりません
It could cost us our lives.
首が飛びますよ
Your Highness,
世子妃様
please go back.
どうぞお引き取り
Please go back.
くださいませ
Yuanji,
元姫姉様
I am serious.
私は本気で言っているの
Think about it.
よく考えてみて
You are making me dizzy.
目が回るわ
I wonder what rank Yuanji received in the exam.
元姫姉様は いったい何品だったのかしら
The results are out!
合格発表だ
The results are out?
合格発表だぞ
Yes.
発表だ
What rank?
何品
First rank.
一品よ
Really?
本当
Now Yuanji
これで元姫姉様も
can finally hold her head high.
やっと面目が立ったわ
She is a female Academician now
女博士になって
and will become a court official.
これからは朝廷に仕えるのね
I need to design
元姫姉様のために
a ceremonial hairpiece for her.
素敵な簪と冠を考えなくちゃ
Where is she now?
姉様は今どこに
She has entered the Eastern Palace
すでに東宮へ
and is about to be granted the title.
まもなく冊封の儀です
He Yuan, the second child of the fifth branch
潁川 中義郎 何氏
of the He family in Yingchuan,
五房の次男 何元
topped the list in this imperial examination.
今回の恩科にて首席と認め
He can enter the Imperial Academy
太学への入学を許し
with the title of Academician,
博士の名を授け
ranked Upper First Grade.
品は上上の一品とする
He Yuan, the second child of the fifth branch of the He family in Yingchuan,
潁川 何氏 五房の次男
pays her respects.
何元 拝首いたします
Rise.
面を上げよ
Thank you, Your Highness.
ありがたき幸せに存じます
Wait.
お待ちを
May I ask, Your Highness,
恐れながら殿下
why you specifically chose He Yuan
なぜ何元を
as the top Academician in the spring examination?
春の試験の首席博士にお選びになったのですか
Is it because of the question about
殿下が選ばれたのは
the difficulties and solutions in waterway construction?
「川筋監修の難点と解決策」という題目のためですか
You're right, Grand Tutor.
太傅様の仰せのとおりです
For this question,
この題目では
all examinees quoted the late Emperor's
受験者は皆 先帝の
"Wenxi Treatise" on waterway management,
「文熹閲考」にある川筋監修法を引用し
using wooden stakes and wicker to reinforce the riverbanks.
杭と柳の枝で堤を固めると論じました
But He Yuan proposed
しかし何元は
the method of bamboo cage with pebbles.
蛇籠の工法を提唱しました
He Yuan, explain it to everyone.
何元 説明せよ
The method of bamboo cage with pebbles
蛇籠とは
means weaving bamboo into cages,
竹で籠を編み
filling them with pebbles, and sinking them into the river.
玉石を詰めて川筋に沈めるものです
The toughness of bamboo cages and the weight of the pebbles
竹籠のしなやかさと玉石の重みにより
can both stabilize the riverbank
川岸を固められ
and withstand the impact of the water flow.
水流の衝撃にも対応できます
This is a method of overcoming hardness with softness.
まさに柔よく剛を制す策です
Let me ask you. How did you, a child of a noble family,
余が聞く 名家の出であるそなたが
come to know the solution?
なぜこの策を知っている
Your Highness,
殿下
I learned this from a criminal.
ある罪人から教わりました
A criminal?
罪人
I brought him here today.
何元が本日 その者を連れてまいりました
His name is...
名は
Liu Zhaolin.
柳昭林と申します
I'm Liu Zhaolin, a criminal.
罪人 柳昭林
Greetings, Prince Qi.
岐王様に拝謁いたします
Liu Zhaolin?
柳昭林
Aren't you dead?
そなたはすでに死んだはずでは
Grand Tutor wanted me
太傅様は私を
to die in the Court of Judicial Review,
大理寺で死なせるおつもりでしたが
but Young Lord Xiao saved me.
蕭世子様がお救いくださいました
I met Grand Tutor in the bookstore.
私は太傅様と書局で知り合いました
He said that if I wanted to stand out,
太傅様は言いました 出世したくば
I must first learn to bow my head.
まず頭を下げることを学べと
As long as I forged the account books
太傅様のために
of Prince Jing'an's Mansion for him,
靖安王府の帳簿を偽造し
framing their family for colluding with foreign enemies,
王府が外敵と結託したとでっち上げさえすれば
he would give me a chance to enter official service.
出仕の機会を与えると約束されました
So I bowed my head.
私は頭を下げました
I deceived the former Heir's Consort
私は靖安王府の
of Prince Jing'an's Mansion
先代の世子妃様を欺きました
and tricked her into giving me the Xiaos' private letters.
妃様の手から蕭氏の私信をだまし取りました
In Lane 3 of Shanghe Ward, a place arranged by the Grand Tutor,
太傅様が手配した上河坊三巷で
I spent 3 whole months practicing
３か月もの間 書き続けました
until my forged handwriting
本物と見紛うほどの
was convincing enough to pass as genuine.
筆跡を偽造したのです
But later, when the case of Prince Jing'an's Mansion broke out,
しかしその後 靖安王府の件が発覚すると
he wanted to silence me.
口封じのために私を殺そうとしました
I saw the method of bamboo cage with pebbles
この蛇籠は
in the Grand Tutor's study.
太傅様の書斎で見たものです
He has been studying this method for over a decade.
十数年にわたり この工法を研究されていました
Yes, I was the one who ordered
靖安王府の罪状は
Liu Zhaolin and others to fabricate
確かにわしが
the charges against Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
柳昭林らに偽造させたものだ
And I have indeed been studying
そしてわしは確かに
the method of bamboo cage with pebbles.
蛇籠を研究してきた
But do you know
だがそなたらは知っておるか
the origin of this method?
この蛇籠の工法の由来を
Back then, the An and Lu families
かつて安陸の二氏は
used exactly this method for waterway management.
まさにこの蛇籠で川筋を監修したのだ
But at that time, this method was framed as evidence
だが この工法は当時 でっち上げにより
that the An and Lu families had deliberately damaged the waterways
安陸が川筋を意図的に破壊し
and colluded with Northern Qin.
北秦と結託したとされ
They were charged with treason.
反逆罪に問われた
As a result, for over 20 years,
その結果 二十数年間
no one dared use this method.
誰もこの工法を使わなくなったのだ
If Your Highness acknowledges this method,
もし殿下がこの蛇籠の工法をお認めになれば
that would prove that Emperor Wenxi was mistaken
文熹帝が誤りで
and that the An and Lu families were wrongfully convicted!
安陸の二氏の件は冤罪だったと証明することになりませんか
Brother.
兄上
The model of the bamboo cage with pebbles?
蛇籠の模型です
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
you knew all along that Brother and I were studying this method?
余と兄上がこの工法を研究していたのを 知っていたな
Everything is ready.
準備は整いました
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
are you going to clear the An and Lu families' names today?
まさか今日 安陸の二氏の汚名をそそぐおつもりか
If so,
そうなれば
I'm afraid the posthumous reputations of Emperor and Empress Wenxi
文熹帝の死後の名声は
cannot be preserved.
地に落ちましょうぞ
I don't care about
太傅がどうあろうと
the Grand Tutor
過去がどうあろうと
or the past.
孤の知ったことではない
What I care about is how to construct the waterways,
孤が案じているのは川筋をいかに監修するかだ
how to save the people
いかにして天下の民を
from the suffering of floods,
水害の苦しみから救い
and how to open the grain canal to the Northern Border as soon as possible.
速やかに北境への兵糧道を拓くかだ
If this method is right,
もしそれが正しいのなら
it shouldn't be buried.
埋もれさせてはならない
Xie Jiayu,
謝嘉魚さん
are you willing to help me?
手を貸してはくれぬか
The case of the An and Lu families' treason has long been settled.
安陸の反逆は 覆らぬ罪状です
And this method of bamboo cages with pebbles
そして この竹籠に玉石を詰める工法は
has not been used for over 20 years.
二十数年 誰も使っておりません
Then how can we prove
では いかにして
whether this method works or not?
この工法の真偽を証明なさるのですか
Then please allow me the chance
ならば今日 この東宮で
to prove it today in the Eastern Palace.
何元に証明の機会を与えよう
I, Xiao Yao, pay my respects to Your Highness.
臣 蕭堯 殿下に拝謁いたします
I, Xiao Yao, a disgraced subject,
罪臣 蕭堯
Ever since the waterway collapsed,
川筋が崩落してより
I have not slept a single night.
この臣は夜も眠れぬ日々でした
Fortunately, I received guidance from Mr. Liu,
幸いにも柳先生にご教授いただき
and with the help of the Heir's Consort,
世子妃様のお力添えを得て
I crafted this bamboo cage with pebbles.
この蛇籠を製作いたしました
I humbly ask Your Highness to grant permission for a trial.
どうか殿下 お試しの許可を
Permission granted.
許す
Thank you, Your Highness.
はっ ありがたき幸せ
Assemble it.
組み立て
Add water.
注水
The pebbles in this cage
この籠の中の玉石は
must be 70% angular stones and 30% rounded stones,
七分角があり三分丸いものを選び
with the stones arranged from the bottom up in a spiral shape.
下から上へ渦を巻くように積み上げます
The 3rd piece is the key.
この三つ目が肝心です
If a fully round one is used,
全て丸い石を選べば
the water will disperse like a defeated army.
水の勢いは統率を失った兵のごとく散り散りになりましょう
It's done.
成功だ
Look, the water flow has slowed down.
見ろ 水の流れが緩やかになった
The house didn't collapse.
家も倒れていない
I wonder if what you have seen today
今日のこの光景で
can untie the knot in your heart, Grand Tutor.
太傅の心のわだかまりは解けましたかな
Your Highness.
殿下
If we don't correct Emperor Wenxi's mistake today,
本日 文熹帝の過ちを正さねば
I'm sure more people
さらに多くの民が
will suffer from the floods.
水害に苦しむことになりましょう
Your Highness, please give your judgment.
本日 どうか殿下 ご明断を
Back then, to seize power from the noble families,
かつて文熹帝は名家の権力を奪うため
Emperor Wenxi used the waterway construction case as a pretext
治水事業を口実に
to frame the An and Lu families for colluding with Northern Qin.
安陸の二氏が北秦と内通したと でっち上げた
It plunged Ye into endless internal strife,
その結果 大鄴は取り返しのつかぬ内乱に陥った
allowing Northern Qin to take the opportunity to march south and overrun the Capital.
北秦はその機に乗り南下し 上京を蹂躙したのだ
This tragedy was single-handedly caused by Emperor Wenxi,
この悲劇は まさに文熹帝が招いたものであり
and it was a disaster born from the conflict between the noble families and the common people.
名家と寒門の争いが生んだ災禍でもある
If we do not abandon the divide between nobles and commoners
名家と寒門の区別をなくし
and clear the names of the An and Lu families,
安陸の二氏の汚名をそそがねば
the tragedy of the Capital will surely repeat itself.
上京の悲劇は必ずや繰り返される
Emperor and Empress Wenxi were not gods,
文熹帝とて神ではない
and the world should not be defined
そして天下は
only by the divide between nobles and commoners.
名家と寒門に分かれるべきではなく
Above all, the world cannot depend on a single person.
一人の人間の手に委ねられるべきでもないのだ
And that person in your hearts,
そして そなたたちの心にいる
the god-like Crown Prince Wenxi,
神のごとき文熹太子だが
actually
実は
died long ago on his way south to Jiankang.
とうに南の剣慷へ向かう道中で死んでいるのだ
Pass on my decree.
孤の勅命を伝えよ
Clear the names of the An and Lu families.
安陸の二氏の汚名をそそげ
All false charges against them
全ての冤罪を
shall be dismissed.
晴らすものとする
Take in their orphans,
その遺児を引き取り
allow them to return to their native places,
戸籍を戻させ
and send them to the Imperial Academy for education.
太学にて養育せよ
Also,
勅命である
Xiao Yao shall be stripped of all official titles
蕭堯の全官職を剝奪し
and banished to Lingnan to address the flooding along the grain canal.
嶺南にて兵糧路の水害を解決する罰を科す
I will do my utmost
臣は身を粉にして働き
for Ye
大鄴のため
until my dying day.
死ぬまで尽くします
My wish is fulfilled.
臣の望みは これで果たされました
I...
臣は
am willing to plead guilty.
罪に服します
Then there will be no further punishment.
罪に服すか ならば罪には問わぬ
I hope you will retire and return to your hometown,
太傅には官を辞して故郷に帰り
reopen your academy,
学問所を再興し
devote yourself to scholarship,
学問に専心されよ
and no longer get involved in political affairs.
決して政に関わってはならぬ
I accept the decree.
臣 御意
Liu Zhaolin and the scholars from Lane 3 of Shanghe Ward
柳昭林と上河坊三巷の学徒は
forged handwriting and account books
筆跡と帳簿を偽造し
to frame Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
靖安王府を陥れた
Considering that this arose from the divide between nobles and commoners,
発端が世族と庶民の不公平にあり
and that they have acknowledged their wrongdoing,
過ちを悔い改めたことに免じ
I shall show leniency
情状を酌量し
and banish them 800 li away.
八百里の流罪に処す
I accept the decree.
罪人 御意
Your Highness, the divide between nobles and commoners
殿下 世族と庶民の不公平は
has long plagued Ye.
まさに大鄴の病弊にございます
Please eradicate it at its root
何とぞ殿下には 禍根を断ち
and establish the spring examination as a permanent system
春の試験を常制とし
to ensure fairness.
公平を正されますよう
Granted.
許す